<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks | Nikhil Kaza</title>
    <link>https://nkaza.github.io/event/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://nkaza.github.io/event/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2018-2025 Nikhil Kaza</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 08:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://nkaza.github.io/media/icon_hu1ca6a6912ef6c300619228a995d3f134_46128_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/event/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Spatial Analysis in R</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/advanced-spatial-analysis-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/advanced-spatial-analysis-in-r/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Analysis in R</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/spatial-analysis-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/spatial-analysis-in-r/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualisation Principles</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/visualisation-principles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/visualisation-principles/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to R &amp; Urban Analytics</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/introduction-to-r-urban-analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/introduction-to-r-urban-analytics/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data driven approaches to quantifying relationships between urban form &amp; livability</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/data-driven-approaches-to-quantifying-relationships-between-urban-form-livability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/data-driven-approaches-to-quantifying-relationships-between-urban-form-livability/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Against the Idea of Implementation in Planning</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/against-the-idea-of-implementation-in-planning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/against-the-idea-of-implementation-in-planning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why are many plans not implemented? Common explanations are planners have little power,
they fail to account for political or environmental uncertainty in the plans or they failed to
include enough voices during the planning process. The theoretical frameworks on which
we base our understanding of plans focus on implementation as a key evaluative mechanism.
I challenge the premise that plans realise their potential only when they are implemented.
Monitoring implementation of plans presupposes that we know what plans there are to monitor.
Such monitoring privileges published plans and ignores all the other plans that guide urban
development. It assumes that the decision situations in which plans are used are observable.
By jettisoning implementation as a key criterion by which to evaluate the effectiveness of plans, we can begin to focus on the myriad ways in which plan makers and others use plans. We can instead ask, ‘How are these plans used? Who uses them? When are they useful? How to make
useful plans?’ With these questions, we can create different evaluative frameworks for different
types of plans. Some unimplementable plans are worth making.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Form and Transportation Energy Consumption</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/urban-form-and-transportation-energy-consumption/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/urban-form-and-transportation-energy-consumption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transportation energy is a significant portion of the energy consumption of the US economy. While various policies such as changing the fuel mix and alternative fuels are proposed to make the system more efficient, the efficacy of land use policies such as changing the urban form and densification have been subject to considerable debate. In this paper, I use a rich dataset compiled from different sources to test the effectiveness of urban form on energy consumption in the transportation sector. I proxy the consumption with retail sales from gas stations for most of the conterminous United States at a county level. Using both demographic, economic and landscape characteristics of urban form I tease out the effect of different dimensions on energy consumption. I find that compact and contiguous urban form is modestly associated with lower energy consumption and is more important than demographic concentration in explaining the variance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Removing Federal Subsidies Discourage Development? An Evaluation of the Impact of the U.S. Coastal Barrier Resources Act</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/does-removing-federal-subsidies-discourage-development-an-evaluation-of-the-impact-of-the-u.s.-coastal-barrier-resources-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/does-removing-federal-subsidies-discourage-development-an-evaluation-of-the-impact-of-the-u.s.-coastal-barrier-resources-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Urban development relies on many factors to remain viable, including infrastructure, services, and
government provisions and subsidies. However, in situations involving federal or state level policy, development responds not just to one regulatory signal, but also to multiple signals from
overlapping and competing jurisdictions. The 1982 U.S. Coastal Barrier Resources Act (CoBRA)
offers an opportunity to study when and how development restrictions and economic disincentives
protect natural resources by stopping or slowing urban development in management regimes with
distributed authority and responsibility. CoBRA prohibits federal financial assistance for
infrastructure, post-storm disaster relief, and flood insurance in designated sections (system units) of coastal barriers. How has CoBRA’s removal of these subsidies affected rates and types of urban development? Using building footprint and real estate data (n=1,385,552 parcels), we compare
density of built structures, land use types, residential house size, and land values within and outside of system units in eight Southeast and Gulf Coast US states. We show that CoBRA is associated with reduced development rates in coastal barrier zones. We also demonstrate how local responses may counteract withdrawal of federal subsidies. As attention increases towards improving urban resilience in high hazard areas, this work contributes to understanding how limitations on infrastructure and insurance subsidies can affect outcomes under overlapping jurisdictions with competing goals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
