<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>urban-change | Nikhil Kaza</title>
    <link>https://nkaza.github.io/tag/urban-change/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://nkaza.github.io/tag/urban-change/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>urban-change</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2018-2023 Nikhil Kaza</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 09:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://nkaza.github.io/media/icon_hu1ca6a6912ef6c300619228a995d3f134_46128_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>urban-change</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/tag/urban-change/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Removing Federal Subsidies Discourage Development? An Evaluation of the Impact of the U.S. Coastal Barrier Resources Act</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/does-removing-federal-subsidies-discourage-development-an-evaluation-of-the-impact-of-the-u.s.-coastal-barrier-resources-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/does-removing-federal-subsidies-discourage-development-an-evaluation-of-the-impact-of-the-u.s.-coastal-barrier-resources-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Urban development relies on many factors to remain viable, including infrastructure, services, and
government provisions and subsidies. However, in situations involving federal or state level policy, development responds not just to one regulatory signal, but also to multiple signals from
overlapping and competing jurisdictions. The 1982 U.S. Coastal Barrier Resources Act (CoBRA)
offers an opportunity to study when and how development restrictions and economic disincentives
protect natural resources by stopping or slowing urban development in management regimes with
distributed authority and responsibility. CoBRA prohibits federal financial assistance for
infrastructure, post-storm disaster relief, and flood insurance in designated sections (system units) of coastal barriers. How has CoBRA’s removal of these subsidies affected rates and types of urban development? Using building footprint and real estate data (n=1,385,552 parcels), we compare
density of built structures, land use types, residential house size, and land values within and outside of system units in eight Southeast and Gulf Coast US states. We show that CoBRA is associated with reduced development rates in coastal barrier zones. We also demonstrate how local responses may counteract withdrawal of federal subsidies. As attention increases towards improving urban resilience in high hazard areas, this work contributes to understanding how limitations on infrastructure and insurance subsidies can affect outcomes under overlapping jurisdictions with competing goals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Development, Coastal Infrastructure and Policy </title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/project/coastal-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/project/coastal-policy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The wind-swept, isolated beauty of coastal barriers has always attracted people. Coastal areas in general have undergone substantial population growth: from 1970 to 2010, the population of U.S. coastal counties increased by 34.8 million (39 percent).  During this time, many of these isolated outposts of sand have undergone a boom in second-home and resort development (Crawford, et al., 2013), with coastal counties issuing an average of over 1300 building permits each day between 2000 and 2010 (Crossett, et al., 2013). The increase in coastal population strains the carrying capacities of coastal land and water. The low elevation, narrowness, and shifting sands of coastal barriers make them high-risk places for development. It is not uncommon for houses on coastal barriers to be washed away, rebuilt, and then destroyed again by a subsequent storm (Salvesen 2005). Growing populations and increased development result in greater damage from natural disasters and greater difficulty in evacuating coastal residents, as past coastal storms have vividly illustrated (e.g., hurricanes Sandy and Katrina).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, the United States government has encouraged private development on coastal barriers through financial assistance for the construction of highways and bridges, water supply and wastewater treatment facilities, and beach stabilization projects (Glavovic and Smith, 2014; Burby, et al., 1999; Beatley, et al., 2002). Federal disaster assistance and flood insurance also have facilitated coastal development by transferring much of the risks and costs of development from the private sector to the public sector (DOI, 1983; Beatley, et al, 2002; Leichenko and Thomas, 2012). Significant literature –pertaining to coastal development as well as other hazardous areas such as floodplains – now argues that federal subsidies have perpetuated a cycle of subsidized development, destruction, and subsidized redevelopment (Berke et al., 2012). After a major coastal storm or hurricane sweeps across a coastal barrier, damaging or destroying homes, shops, roads, and water and sewer lines, federal disaster relief helps rebuild the damaged properties and infrastructure (Gillis and Barringer, 2012; Bagstad, et al., 2007; Burby, 2006).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims to test the long-term effects of the withdrawal of development subsidies on development in coastal areas. Land markets respond to various kinds of signals about demand, supply, cost of construction, available tax credits, and subsidies. Growth controls – which can include development regulations or subsidy restrictions – are common local policy tools that have been shown to generallyincrease housing prices in the community (Elliot, 1981; Dowall and Landis 1982; and Katz and Rosen, 1987). While impacts on aggregate housing affordability depend upon the details of implementation, house value impacts of growth control policies are especially strong within the areas of control, making them a good indicator of policy effectiveness (Dawkins and Nelson 2002).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;collaborators&#34;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://todd.bendor.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Todd BenDor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ie.unc.edu/people/salvesen/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. David Salvesen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kyle Onda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jordan Branham&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Change &amp; Its Impacts</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/project/urban-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/project/urban-change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is notoriously hard to measure and track &amp;lsquo;urban&amp;rsquo; as there are multiple dimensions to it; social, demographic, geographic, perceputal, environmental and  patterns of growth and decline. In this long standing research project, we seek to provide some novel ways of understanding our urban environments operate and change, and how those changes shape our behaviours. In doing so, we seek to understand the limitations as well as the suitability of measurements from various types of data streams (administrative to environmental sensors). By tracking the changes in these measurements, we seek characterise urban change around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2015.03.008&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;McCarty &amp;amp; Kaza(2015)&lt;/a&gt; we used data from different air pollution sensors in a county to calculate the number of days with bad air quality in a year. We then relate it to &lt;a href=&#34;https://sia.planning.unc.edu/post/urban-morphology-landscape-metrics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;urban fragmentation metrics&lt;/a&gt; obtained from land cover data. We find that while counties with higher forest land area have higher number of polluted days. This effect is mitigated when these forests are closer to urban areas. Similarly, urban form measured as land use density or type or measured as geomorphometry have been shown to have different  on energy consumption patterns in cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, urban economy is also rapidly changing. One narrative of the cities argues for understanding and applauding the renaissance of cities during the decades of 1990s and 2000s (comeback cities). Another narrative suggest that this renaissance is highly uneven and is concentrated in innovative regions, while cities in the rest of the   regions (backwards) are loosing ground. To provide evidence for explanations and to disentangle the causes of these phenomena are some of the main motivations of this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A natural outgrowth of this research is produce different plausible futures of urban form in different places. Since the configuration as well as the extent of urban form matter for climate as well as environmental outcomes, we seek to develop methods for projecting different futures based on various patterns, we observe in the past and learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to expand the repertoire of urban areas to include areas from various parts of the world, including Asia, Africa and South America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;collaborators&#34;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.twilliamlester.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;T. William Lester&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.urban-three.com/josh-mccarty/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Josh McCarty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
