<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>urban-form | Nikhil Kaza</title>
    <link>https://nkaza.github.io/tag/urban-form/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://nkaza.github.io/tag/urban-form/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>urban-form</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2018-2025 Nikhil Kaza</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 16:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://nkaza.github.io/media/icon_hu1ca6a6912ef6c300619228a995d3f134_46128_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>urban-form</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/tag/urban-form/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Form and Transportation Energy Consumption</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/urban-form-and-transportation-energy-consumption/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/urban-form-and-transportation-energy-consumption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transportation energy is a significant portion of the energy consumption of the US economy. While various policies such as changing the fuel mix and alternative fuels are proposed to make the system more efficient, the efficacy of land use policies such as changing the urban form and densification have been subject to considerable debate. In this paper, I use a rich dataset compiled from different sources to test the effectiveness of urban form on energy consumption in the transportation sector. I proxy the consumption with retail sales from gas stations for most of the conterminous United States at a county level. Using both demographic, economic and landscape characteristics of urban form I tease out the effect of different dimensions on energy consumption. I find that compact and contiguous urban form is modestly associated with lower energy consumption and is more important than demographic concentration in explaining the variance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Removing Federal Subsidies Discourage Development? An Evaluation of the Impact of the U.S. Coastal Barrier Resources Act</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/does-removing-federal-subsidies-discourage-development-an-evaluation-of-the-impact-of-the-u.s.-coastal-barrier-resources-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/does-removing-federal-subsidies-discourage-development-an-evaluation-of-the-impact-of-the-u.s.-coastal-barrier-resources-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Urban development relies on many factors to remain viable, including infrastructure, services, and
government provisions and subsidies. However, in situations involving federal or state level policy, development responds not just to one regulatory signal, but also to multiple signals from
overlapping and competing jurisdictions. The 1982 U.S. Coastal Barrier Resources Act (CoBRA)
offers an opportunity to study when and how development restrictions and economic disincentives
protect natural resources by stopping or slowing urban development in management regimes with
distributed authority and responsibility. CoBRA prohibits federal financial assistance for
infrastructure, post-storm disaster relief, and flood insurance in designated sections (system units) of coastal barriers. How has CoBRA’s removal of these subsidies affected rates and types of urban development? Using building footprint and real estate data (n=1,385,552 parcels), we compare
density of built structures, land use types, residential house size, and land values within and outside of system units in eight Southeast and Gulf Coast US states. We show that CoBRA is associated with reduced development rates in coastal barrier zones. We also demonstrate how local responses may counteract withdrawal of federal subsidies. As attention increases towards improving urban resilience in high hazard areas, this work contributes to understanding how limitations on infrastructure and insurance subsidies can affect outcomes under overlapping jurisdictions with competing goals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Irregular settlements</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/project/irregular-settlements/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/project/irregular-settlements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About a third of the urban population in the world (~830 million) live in irregular/informal settlements/favelas/shanty towns/slums (United Nations Development Programme 2017). Whatever names these neighbourhoods take around the world, these settlements are at the core of many urban regions around the world; they provide affordable housing for urban poor but at high social and health costs. In urban areas, these types of settlements can constitute 30%-60% of the city and in some regions around the world, these settlements are the dominant urban form surpassing the formal settlements (Busgeeth et al. 2008; Kombe 2005). While denizens of these neighbourhoods may lack access to sanitation and other urban services or security of tenure, they tend develop bottom-up institutions (e.g. informal housing markets, vote banks) in myriad of ways that are interesting for students of urban politics and systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, to study these phenomena, we need to know where these settlements are and how they change over time. Because official estimates grossly undercount or ignore people in these settlements, it is hard to study them. Very little is known about how the settlements change over time and how quickly they are changing in response to contested claims by different groups (Roy 2009).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the world, these settlements have distinct morphological characteristics. They are often associated with poor housing quality, cramped houses, uneven building heights, lack of sanitation and drinking water infrastructure, uneven quality of construction, lack of vegetative cover, small setbacks and narrow roads. The diversity of these areas pose a challenges for coming up with consistent monitoring and for creating robust methods for detecting and characterizing settlements (Kit, Lüdeke, and Reckien 2012; Taubenböck and Kraff 2013; Weeks et al. 2007).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the availability of high quality, high resolution, high frequency satellite imagery, it is becoming increasingly possible to develop methods that will reduce the on-ground monitoring and data collection costs. The goal of this project is to map and validate the irregular settlements in entirety of  metropolitan areas in India. We are focusing on Bengaluru, Delhi, Jaipur, Hyderabad and Patna as the initial set of cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;collaborators&#34;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Dr. Raju Vastavai] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.csc.ncsu.edu/people/rrvatsav&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.csc.ncsu.edu/people/rrvatsav&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Dr. Anirudh Krishna] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://sanford.duke.edu/people/faculty/krishna-anirudh&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://sanford.duke.edu/people/faculty/krishna-anirudh&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://polisci.duke.edu/people/erik-wibbels&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Erik Wibbels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peak Oil, Urban Form and Public Health: Exploring the Connections</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/publication/kaza-2011-dq/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/publication/kaza-2011-dq/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
