<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy-policy | Nikhil Kaza</title>
    <link>https://nkaza.github.io/tag/energy-policy/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://nkaza.github.io/tag/energy-policy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>energy-policy</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2018-2025 Nikhil Kaza</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 16:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://nkaza.github.io/media/icon_hu1ca6a6912ef6c300619228a995d3f134_46128_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>energy-policy</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/tag/energy-policy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Form and Transportation Energy Consumption</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/urban-form-and-transportation-energy-consumption/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/talk/urban-form-and-transportation-energy-consumption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transportation energy is a significant portion of the energy consumption of the US economy. While various policies such as changing the fuel mix and alternative fuels are proposed to make the system more efficient, the efficacy of land use policies such as changing the urban form and densification have been subject to considerable debate. In this paper, I use a rich dataset compiled from different sources to test the effectiveness of urban form on energy consumption in the transportation sector. I proxy the consumption with retail sales from gas stations for most of the conterminous United States at a county level. Using both demographic, economic and landscape characteristics of urban form I tease out the effect of different dimensions on energy consumption. I find that compact and contiguous urban form is modestly associated with lower energy consumption and is more important than demographic concentration in explaining the variance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local Energy Policy &amp; Planning</title>
      <link>https://nkaza.github.io/project/energy-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nkaza.github.io/project/energy-policy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Energy, a quintessential private good, poses a conundrum for planners. The weaknesses of the argument that public goods are proper domain of planning become quite apparent, when we consider energy production and transmission infrastructure. Production of useful energy is a highly technical process, yet the political implications of such production and transmission inevitably draws planners into the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this thread of research, I seek to understand how traditional planning at the local and regional level wittingly and unwittingly intersect with energy production and consumption. In particular, I am interested in the idea that local governments can use their influence on urban form to influence energy production and consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;collaborators&#34;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://planning.unc.edu/faculty/song/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Yan Song&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://chaosuli.web.unc.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Chaosu Li&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://communitycapital.unc.edu/person/roberto-g-quercia/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Roberto Quercia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
